RG 049, Veterans' Advisory Commission
Connecticut State Library
Veterans' Advisory Commission records
1943-1949
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Veterans' Advisory Commission
20.25 cubic feet
The Commission planned for the orderly readjustment and reemployment of returning veterans and displaced war workers and coordinated the efforts of all State, local and private agencies working toward that end.
RG049
1971-003
Historical Note
In the summer of 1943 Governor Raymond E. Baldwin, Jr. appointed the Connecticut Reemployment Commission to make plans for the orderly readjustment and reemployment of returning veterans and displaced war workers and to coordinate the efforts of all State, local and private agencies working toward that end. Carl A. Gray became chairperson, and he and most of the twenty-five or so unpaid members continued to serve until 1949, even though changes in title and function took place. A small full-time staff and director (James M. Quinn during most of the period) performed support functions.
In 1945 the General Assembly made the Commission a statutory agency, dropping its responsibility for displaced war workers and changing its name to the Veterans Reemployment and Advisory Commission. The agency operated principally by stimulating and assisting in the creation and operation of local disseminating information about employment and training opportunities and services available to veterans, and by publishing various bulletins, guides and a monthly, Reemploymnet.
The agency's name changed after the fiscal year 1947 to Veterans Advisory Commission. The Commission went out of existence on June 30, 1949.
Scope and Content
This record group contains minutes of meetings, special memoranda, lists of committee members, "town planning survey" material, a general file, a subkect file, field representatives' file, training files, public relations file, personnel and financial records.
Related Material
RG 005:029, Raymond E. Baldwin gubernatorial records, 1943-1945. See under headings such as "Apprenticeship Council", "Gray Committee" and others.
RG 040, Post-War Planning Board, 1943-1945
RG 050, War Council, 1940-1945
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Reemployment Commission; Connecticut. Veterans' Advisory Commission; Connecticut. Veterans Reemployment and Advisory Commission
Persons:
Gray, Carl A. (Carl Albert), 1900-; Quinn, James M.
Subjects:
Connecticut. Reemployment Commission -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Veterans' Advisory Commission -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Veterans Reemployment and Advisory Commission -- Records and correspondence; Labor supply -- Connecticut; Reconstruction (1939-1941) -- Connecticut; Unemployed -- Connecticut; Veterans -- Connecticut; Veterans -- Employment -- Connecticut; Veterans -- Education -- Connecticut; Veterans -- Employment -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Financial records; Membership lists; Minutes; Memorandums; Notes; Personnel records; Radio scripts; Press releases; Reports; Serials
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
Found in the State Library’s Oak Street building in 1971, this record group was badly disarranged and some records appear to have been lost. After study and appraisal, some records were weeded out and staff put the remainder into something approaching their original order.
Container List
- Records, 1943-1949
  - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1943 August-1949 January; 5 binders (Box 1)
    Mimeographed minutes of the meetings of the Reemployment Commission and its successor and subordinate committees.
    Arranged chronologically.
    There is substantial duplication.
  - 1A. Miscellaneous (Box 1A)
    - Lists of special memoranda and radio broadcasts, 1 binder (Box 1A)
    - Connecticut Laws Affecting Veterans and Their DependentsConnecticut Veterans Reemployment and Advisory Commission, November 1945 (Box 1A)
    - Convention of the Veterans' Advisory Commission, Hotel Bond, Hartford, 1946 February 27; 1 photograph (Box 1A)
  - 2. Special memoranda, 1945 August-1949 April; 6 binders (Box 1-2)
    Mimeographed memoranda transmitting information or instructions to local offices and others.
    Arranged numerically (1-351) and chronologically.
    Each binder includes a table of contents.
  - 3. Lists of committee members, 1943-1949; 4 binders (Box 2)
    Lists of members of the Commission and of various affiliated and subordinate bodies. Three of the binders contain lists, on standard forms, of local committee members.
    Local lists arranged alphabetically by town.
    There is some duplication in the three sets.
  - 4. "Town Planning Survey" material, 1944 June-November; 2 binders (Box 2)
    The Survey, conducted by three members of the War Council staff, was carried out "to explore conditions having bearing upon State and local post-war planning." Interviews with local officials were held in order to complete detailed questionnaire reports for each town.
    Loose in the first bionder is a draft report analyzing the data and summarizing the project (apparently written by Ralph Pendleton.
    Arranged alphabetically by town.
  - 5. General file, 1943-1949
    Correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes and reference materials pertaining to the wokr of the Commission, veterans' affairs generally, employment and training matters, and similar programs in other states.
    Arranged alphabetically by subkject. Somewhat disarranged and lacking the first part A-Cl.
    - College Training - D (Box 3)
    - E-Education (Box 4)
    - Employees-H (Box 5)
    - I-Natural (Box 6)
    - Naturalization-R (Box 7)
    - S-T (Box 8)
    - U-Z (Box 9)
  - 6. Subject file, 1943-1946
    Correspondence, drafts of reports, notes nad memoranda. This may have been the office file of the Director or his Deputy. It contains (under "Governor") copies of the annual reports of the Commission.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - A-P (Box 10)
    - R-Z (Box 11)
  - 7. Field representatives' file, 1944-1949
    Correspondence, memoranda and reports of Major R.B. Cate, Chief Field Representative, and his associates, principally pertaining to their interviews with local officials about local reemployment and training programs.
    Arranged by subject, with a file of copies of reports in reverse chronological order.
    - Subject files (Box 12)
    - Report files (Box 13)
  - 8. Training files, 1946-1949
    Correspondence and other mateirals pertaining to the "on-the-job" training and apprentice training programs carried on in cooperation with the Department of Education and other agencies. Most of the materials consist of ntoices and lists of approvals and withdrawals of approval for specific employers.
    Arranged by subject or chronologically.
    - On-the-job training files (Box 14-16)
    - Apprentice files (Box 17)
  - 9. Public relations file, 1944-1948 (Box 18)
    Correspondence, drafts and copies of publications, press releases, radio scripts and other public relations and informational material disseminated my trhe Commission. Included is a complete file of the monthly Reemployment Bulletin, September 1944-July 1947, a file of press releases, a series of radio scripts, and copies of other printed nad mimeographed publications.
  - 10. Personnel and financial records, 1945-1948 (Box 19)
    Personnel files for individual staff memebers, service ratings, payrolls, budget materials, commitment lists, and related records.
    Arranged by subject.
  - 11. Miscellaneous, 1945-1948 (Box 20)
    These papers, including some significant material, may perhaps have come from the desk of a senior official. They include drafts and owking notes for a report to the Governor, a compilation of laws relating to veterans, etc.; miinutes of conventions (1946 and 1948) of state directors of veterans' affairs; a history of the War Manpower COmmission in Connecticut (by J. Frank Daly); and other materials.